43. NEAT. The acronym NEAT stands for Not in Education, Employment, or Training. NEAT
usually refers to people who have been out of work, school, and training for some time.
NEAT people often have negative psychological states. Some of these are causes of their
NEAT status, others are results. Many young people become NEAT because they don't have
good job qualifications. In this slow economy, competition for jobs is fierce. Because they
think they have poor qualifications, they may lack confidence. Without confidence, they
may lose motivation and forget how to even set goals, let alone how to achieve them.
Their NEAT status can pull them into a vicious circle. The longer they are away from a job,
the more difficult it is for them to find one and perform in it. According to the Princess
Trust Youth Index of 2010, many NEAT youth feel more negative about the world than their
peers. The 16- to 25-year-old people in the survey were less likely to feel happy or loved
most of the time. They were far more likely to agree with statements like, My life has
no direction, I do not feel valued by those around me, I have nothing to look forward
to, and even, I have felt suicidal. The obvious solution for NEATs is a better economy and
more jobs. More importantly, we need to create a society where being out of work is not a
source of shame. Life is about more than work. We human beings should remember that our lives
are valuable for a huge variety of reasons. A paycheck shouldn't be the only one.